Today's video theme: A Day in the Life of a Student. Let's study hard!
วันนี้ในวิดีโอเราจะพูดถึงเรื่องอะไรเหรอ? คือเรื่อง 'วันหนึ่งของนักเรียน' นะ มาเรียนกันให้เต็มที่เลย!
Scene 1: Morning Rush – Cramming for a Test
ฉากที่ 1: ตื่นเช้าตรู่ เตรียมตัวสอบ
Good morning!
อรุณสวัสดิ์ค่ะ
Oh, good morning!
อ้าว อรุณสวัสดิ์ค่ะ
What time is it now?
ตอนนี้กี่โมงแล้วคะ?
It's 7:30.
เจ็ดโมงครึ่งแล้วค่ะ
Oh no!
แย่แล้ว!
We have a test first period today.
วันนี้คาบแรกมีสอบด้วย
Wait, really?
เอ๊ะ จริงเหรอคะ?
Hurry up!
รีบหน่อยสิคะ
Got it. No time to make breakfast.
ค่ะ ไม่มีเวลาทำอาหารเช้าแล้ว
There's bread on the table.
มีขนมปังอยู่บนโต๊ะนะคะ
Want some?
จะกินไหมคะ?
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
Let's dig in.
ขอทานก่อนนะคะ
Want some coffee too?
จะดื่มกาแฟด้วยไหมคะ?
I'll brew some for you.
เดี๋ยวฉันชงให้ค่ะ
No, no time. Water's fine.
ไม่ละค่ะ ไม่มีเวลาแล้ว ขอน้ำเปล่าก็พอ
Alright.
เข้าใจแล้วค่ะ
Is the test hard?
ข้อสอบยากไหมคะ?
Yeah, I think it's really tough.
ค่ะ คิดว่ายากมากเลย
Did you study a lot last night?
เมื่อคืนอ่านหนังสือเยอะไหมคะ?
Yeah, I was at the library until midnight.
ค่ะ อ่านหนังสือที่ห้องสมุดจนถึงเที่ยงคืน
That's impressive!
เก่งมากเลยนะคะ
You'll do great, I'm sure.
ไม่เป็นไรหรอกค่ะ คุณทำได้แน่นอน
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
I'll do my best!
จะพยายามค่ะ
All set?
เตรียมตัวเสร็จหรือยังคะ?
Yep, everything's in my bag.
ใส่ของในกระเป๋าเรียบร้อยแล้วค่ะ
Alright, let's head out then.
งั้นก็ออกเดินทางกันเถอะค่ะ
Let's go!
ค่ะ ไปกันเลยค่ะ
Check the description and top comment for a link to review today's video! *Note: The site may be removed without notice.
ลิงก์เว็บไซต์สำหรับทบทวนเนื้อหาวิดีโอวันนี้อยู่ในคำอธิบายและคอมเมนต์แรกนะคะ *เว็บไซต์อาจถูกลบโดยไม่แจ้งให้ทราบล่วงหน้า
Scene 2: Commuting and the Weather
ฉากที่ 2: วิธีการเดินทางและสภาพอากาศ
It's so hot every day, isn't it?
ทุกวันนี้ร้อนจริง ๆ เลยนะ
Sure is.
ใช่เลยค่ะ
How are you getting to school today?
วันนี้จะไปโรงเรียนยังไงคะ?
I'm taking the bus.
วันนี้จะไปรถเมล์ค่ะ
I'm biking.
ฉันจะขี่จักรยานไปค่ะ
Let's walk to the bus stop together then.
งั้นไปป้ายรถเมล์ด้วยกันเถอะค่ะ
Sounds good.
ค่ะ ไปด้วยกันค่ะ
How long does it take to bike to school?
ขี่จักรยานไปโรงเรียนใช้เวลากี่นาทีเหรอคะ?
About 15 minutes.
ประมาณสิบห้านาทีค่ะ
That's fast!
เร็วจังเลยนะคะ
The bus takes 20 minutes.
รถเมล์ใช้เวลายี่สิบนาทีค่ะ
But biking's tough on rainy days, so I take the bus.
แต่ถ้าวันไหนฝนตก ขี่จักรยานลำบาก ก็เลยขึ้นรถเมล์ค่ะ
True.
อ๋อ นั่นสินะ
I want a new bike too.
ฉันก็อยากได้จักรยานใหม่เหมือนกัน
Want to go bike shopping this weekend?
สุดสัปดาห์นี้ ไปดูกันไหมคะ?
Sure!
ดีเลยค่ะ
Where's the shop?
มีร้านอยู่ที่ไหนเหรอคะ?
There's a big one in front of the station.
มีร้านใหญ่อยู่หน้าสถานีรถไฟค่ะ
Is it expensive?
สูงไหมคะ
No, I don’t think it’s too expensive.
ไม่ค่ะ ไม่สูงมากหรอกค่ะ
Oh, that’s the bus stop over there, isn’t it?
อ๊ะ นั่นป้ายรถเมล์นะคะ
Yes. Well, I’ll go by bike from here.
ค่ะ ฉันจะขี่จักรยานจากที่นี่แล้วล่ะ
Alright.
เข้าใจแล้วค่ะ
Take care.
ระวังตัวด้วยนะคะ
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
See you later.
ไว้เจอกันทีหลังนะ
Scene 3: Greetings and Forgotten Items
ฉากที่ 3: การทักทายและของที่ลืม / Greetings and Forgotten Items
Good morning!
อรุณสวัสดิ์ค่ะ
You’re early today.
วันนี้มาเร็วจังเลยนะ
Yeah, I arrived a little early.
ค่ะ มาถึงก่อนหน่อยค่ะ
Has the teacher arrived yet?
อาจารย์มาแล้วหรือยังคะ
No, they’re not in the classroom yet.
ยังค่ะ ยังไม่มาในห้องเรียนเลย
I see.
อืม เข้าใจแล้ว
Oh no, I don’t have my eraser.
อ๊ะ ยางลบของฉันหายไปแล้ว
Isn’t it in your bag?
ไม่มีในกระเป๋าหรอ
Hmm, no, it’s not.
อืม ไม่มีค่ะ
I must’ve left it at home.
ลืมไว้ที่บ้านแล้ว
Here, you can use my eraser.
งั้นใช้ยางลบของฉันก่อนก็ได้ค่ะ
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
That’d be a big help.
ช่วยได้เยอะเลย ขอบคุณนะคะ
What’s the first class today?
คาบแรกวันนี้เรียนอะไรเหรอคะ
Japanese grammar.
เรียนไวยากรณ์ภาษาญี่ปุ่นค่ะ
Did you do the homework?
ทำการบ้านแล้วหรือยังคะ
Yeah, I finished it all last night.
ทำแล้วค่ะ ทำเสร็จหมดเมื่อคืนนี้
I haven’t yet.
ฉันยังไม่ได้ทำเลย
I’ve only got three questions left.
เหลืออีกแค่ 3 ข้อเท่านั้น
Was it difficult?
ยากไหมคะ
Yeah, it was really tough.
ยากมากเลยค่ะ
Can you help me with it?
ช่วยสอนหน่อยได้ไหมคะ
Sure, no problem.
ได้เลยค่ะ
Which questions?
ข้อไหนล่ะคะ
The one at the very bottom of this page.
ข้อนี้ที่อยู่ด้านล่างสุดของหน้านี้ค่ะ
Ah, you use this word for that one.
อ๋อ ข้อนี้ใช้คำนี้ค่ะ
Scene 4: Discussing Lunch Plans
ฉากที่ 4: ปรึกษาเรื่องอาหารกลางวัน / Discussing Lunch Plans
It’s already noon.
ตอนนี้ 12 โมงแล้วนะ
Yeah, it is.
ใช่ค่ะ
Should we get lunch?
ไปกินข้าวกลางวันกันไหมคะ
Sure!
ดีเลยค่ะ
What do you want to eat today?
วันนี้จะกินอะไรดีคะ
Should we eat at the cafeteria?
ไปกินที่โรงอาหารกันไหม
I’d rather eat out today.
วันนี้อยากกินข้างนอกมากกว่าค่ะ
How about that restaurant in front of the school?
งั้นไปร้านอาหารหน้าโรงเรียนกันไหมคะ
Is the food good there?
ร้านนั้นอร่อยไหมคะ
Yeah, it is.
ใช่ค่ะ
It’s really good.
อร่อยมากเลยค่ะ
Is it expensive?
สูงไหมคะ
No, the student lunch is only 500 yen, so it’s cheap.
ไม่ค่ะ อาหารกลางวันสำหรับนักเรียนราคา 500 เยนเท่านั้น ถูกด้วย
That sounds great.
ดีจังเลยค่ะ
What do you recommend?
มีเมนูไหนแนะนำบ้างคะ
I think the curry rice is the best.
คิดว่าข้าวแกงกะหรี่อร่อยที่สุดค่ะ
I love curry too.
ฉันก็ชอบกะหรี่เหมือนกัน
Let’s go with that then.
งั้นก็กะหรี่กันเถอะ
There are a lot of people, so let’s hurry.
มีคนเยอะมาก รีบกันหน่อยดีกว่า
Sure is.
ใช่เลยค่ะ
Should we run?
วิ่งไปกันไหม
It’s dangerous, so let’s walk.
อันตรายนะ เดินไปกันดีกว่าค่ะ
Alright.
เข้าใจแล้วค่ะ
Oh, I see the shop now.
อ๊ะ ร้านเห็นแล้วค่ะ
Are there any seats available?
มีที่นั่งไหมคะ
Yeah, it is.
ใช่ค่ะ
There’s an open seat by the window.
มีที่นั่งริมหน้าต่างว่างอยู่นะ
Great!
ดีจังเลย
Let’s sit down.
นั่งกันเถอะ
Scene 5: Mastering Kanji – How to Read and Understand Its Meaning
ฉากที่ 5: การอ่านและความหมายของคันจิ
Excuse me, do you have a moment?
ขอโทษค่ะ มีเรื่องจะถามนิดหน่อยได้ไหมคะ
Sure, what’s up?
ได้ค่ะ มีอะไรเหรอคะ
I can’t read this kanji in the book.
คันจิในหนังสือเล่มนี้อ่านไม่ได้ค่ะ
Which one?
ที่ตรงไหนคะ
Let me see.
ขอดูหน่อยได้ไหมคะ
It’s this one in red.
ตรงตัวอักษรสีแดงนี่ค่ะ
Ah, this reads as *toshokan*.
อ๋อ อันนี้อ่านว่า "โทโชคัง" ค่ะ
*Toshokan*, got it.
"โทโชคัง" ใช่ไหมคะ
What does it mean?
แล้วมันหมายความว่าอะไรคะ
It’s a place with lots of books—a library.
หมายถึงสถานที่ที่มีหนังสือเยอะๆ ค่ะ
Alright.
เข้าใจแล้วค่ะ
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
Don’t you have a dictionary?
คุณมีพจนานุกรมไหมคะ
No, I didn’t bring it today.
วันนี้ไม่ได้เอามาค่ะ
Want to borrow mine?
ให้ยืมพจนานุกรมของฉันไหมคะ
Are you sure?
ได้เหรอคะ
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
Yeah, here you go.
ได้ค่ะ นี่ค่ะ
Studying for tomorrow’s test?
อ่านหนังสือเตรียมสอบพรุ่งนี้เหรอคะ
Yep, that’s right.
ใช่ค่ะ
There’s so much to memorize.
มีอะไรให้จำเยอะเลย
Kanji tests are every week, so it’s tough.
สอบคันจิทุกอาทิตย์เลยลำบากจริงๆ นะคะ
Yeah, but I’m getting better little by little.
ใช่ค่ะ แต่ก็เก่งขึ้นทีละนิดๆ แล้ว
That’s great to hear!
ดีจังเลยค่ะ
I’ll return the dictionary later.
พจนานุกรมจะคืนให้ทีหลังนะคะ
No rush.
ไม่ต้องรีบก็ได้ค่ะ
Whenever works for you.
คืนเมื่อไหร่ก็ได้ค่ะ
Scene 6: Chatting About Part-Time Jobs
ฉากที่ 6: เรื่องงานพาร์ทไทม์
All today’s classes are done, huh?
วันนี้เรียนจบหมดแล้วนะ
Good work today!
เหนื่อยกันแล้วสินะ
I’m so tired.
เหนื่อยมากเลย
Same here.
ฉันก็เหนื่อยเหมือนกัน
What are you up to now?
ต่อจากนี้จะทำอะไรดี
I’ve got my part-time job today.
วันนี้มีงานพาร์ทไทม์ค่ะ
I see.
อืม เข้าใจแล้ว
Where do you work?
ทำงานพาร์ทไทม์ที่ไหนเหรอคะ
At a convenience store near the station.
ที่ร้านสะดวกซื้อใกล้ๆ สถานีรถไฟค่ะ
What are your working hours?
ทำงานกี่โมงถึงกี่โมงคะ
From 5 PM to 9 PM.
ตั้งแต่ 5 โมงเย็นถึง 3 ทุ่มค่ะ
That sounds tough.
เหนื่อยนะเนี่ย
How many days a week do you work?
ทำงานสัปดาห์ละกี่ครั้งคะ
Three days a week.
สัปดาห์ละ 3 ครั้งค่ะ
Do you earn a lot?
ได้เงินเยอะไหมคะ
No, not really.
ไม่ค่อยเยอะเท่าไหร่ค่ะ
But it’s fun!
แต่ก็สนุกดีค่ะ
Do you speak Japanese with customers?
คุยกับลูกค้าเป็นภาษาญี่ปุ่นไหมคะ
Yeah, it is.
ใช่ค่ะ
Every day.
คุยทุกวันค่ะ
That’s great practice!
เป็นการฝึกฝนที่ดีเลย
I want to get a part-time job too.
ฉันอยากทำงานพาร์ทไทม์บ้าง
Well then, should I ask my store manager?
งั้นถามผู้จัดการร้านฉันดีไหม
Really?
จริงเหรอคะ
Please do.
ขอบคุณมากค่ะ
Yeah, it is.
ใช่ค่ะ
Well, I should be going now.
ถ้างั้นฉันขอตัวก่อนนะ
Good luck!
ขอให้โชคดีนะ
See you tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้เจอกัน
Take care on your way home.
กลับบ้านระวังตัวด้วยนะ
Scene 7: Shopping and Preparing Dinner
ฉากที่ 7: ช็อปปิ้งและเตรียมอาหารเย็น
What should we make for dinner tonight?
เย็นนี้จะทำอะไรทานดี
I feel like eating meat.
อยากกินเนื้อจัง
Alright, let's go grocery shopping then.
งั้นไปซื้อของที่ซูเปอร์กันเถอะ
Should we go to the supermarket in front of the station?
ไปซูเปอร์หน้าสถานีไหม
Yes, their vegetables are cheap too.
ไปสิ ที่นั่นผักก็ถูกด้วย
It's so cold inside the store, isn't it?
ในร้านเย็นมากเลยนะ
Yeah, the air conditioning is really strong.
ใช่ แอร์แรงจริง
Where's the meat?
เนื้ออยู่ไหนเหรอ
Over there, next to the fish.
ตรงโน้นค่ะ อยู่ข้างๆ ปลา
Do you prefer pork or beef?
ชอบหมูหรือเนื้อมากกว่ากัน
I like both, but let's go with pork today.
ชอบทั้งคู่ แต่เย็นนี้เอาหมูก็แล้วกัน
Got it. How about this pork?
หมูชิ้นนี้เป็นไงบ้าง
It's 300 yen. That's cheap, so let's get it.
300 เยน ถูกด้วย ซื้ออันนี้เถอะ
What vegetables should we buy?
จะซื้อผักอะไรดี
Let's get some cabbage and onions.
เอากะหล่ำปลีกับหัวหอมกันเถอะ
Oh, and I want eggs too.
เอาไข่ด้วยได้ไหม
We still have eggs in the fridge at home.
ไข่ยังมีในตู้เย็นที่บ้านอยู่นะ
Oh, right. Then this should be enough.
งั้นเอาแค่นี้ก็พอ
Yes, let's head to the checkout.
ใช่ ไปชำระเงินกันเถอะ
I'll pay for this.
ฉันจะจ่ายเอง
Scene 8: A Meal Conversation
ฉากที่ 8: บทสนทนาระหว่างมื้ออาหาร
Dinner's ready!
ข้าวเสร็จแล้วจ้า
Wow, it smells amazing!
ว้าว หอมจังเลย
Today, we have stir-fried pork and vegetables.
วันนี้เป็นผัดหมูกับผัก
That looks delicious.
ดูน่าอร่อยจัง
Let's dig in.
ขอทานก่อนนะคะ
How does it taste?
รสชาติเป็นยังไงบ้าง
It's really good!
อร่อยมากเลย
It's a little spicy, though.
เผ็ดนิดหน่อยนะ
Sorry about that.
ขอโทษที
I love spicy food.
ฉันชอบอาหารเผ็ด
It's okay.
ไม่เป็นไร
I like spicy food too.
ฉันก็ชอบเผ็ดเหมือนกัน
Would you like some tea?
จะดื่มชาไหม
Yes, please.
เอาเลย ขอบคุณ
How was your part-time job today?
งานพาร์ทไทม์วันนี้เป็นยังไงบ้าง
It was busy, but fun.
ยุ่งแต่สนุกดี
That's great to hear.
ดีจังเลย
Are you tired?
เหนื่อยไหม
Yes, my feet hurt a little.
เหนื่อยนิดหน่อย ขาเจ็บ
Take a bath and rest well.
ไปอาบน้ำแล้วพักผ่อนเยอะๆ นะ
Yes, I will.
ค่ะ จะทำอย่างนั้น
This dish is absolutely delicious, isn't it?
อาหารนี้อร่อยจริงๆ เลยนะ
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
Would you like some more?
จะกินอีกไหม
Yes, please. Just a little more.
ค่ะ ขออีกนิดหน่อยนะคะ
There's plenty, so help yourself to as much as you'd like!
มีเยอะเลย กินให้หมดได้เลยนะ
I will! It's so good, I'll finish it all.
ค่ะ อร่อยมากเลย กินให้หมดแน่ๆ
Scene 9: Daily Conversations and Hobbies
ฉากที่ 9: บทสนทนาในชีวิตประจำวันและงานอดิเรก
Mind if I turn on the TV?
เปิดทีวีได้ไหม
Yeah, here you go.
ได้ค่ะ นี่ค่ะ
Is there anything interesting on?
มีรายการอะไรสนุกๆ บ้างไหม
My favorite anime is starting now.
ตอนนี้อนิเมะที่ชอบกำลังจะเริ่มแล้ว
What kind of anime is it?
อนิเมะเรื่องอะไรเหรอ
It's about high school students playing sports.
เป็นอนิเมะเกี่ยวกับนักเรียนมัธยมที่เล่นกีฬา
Oh, that sounds interesting!
ว้าว ฟังดูน่าสนุกจัง
I'd love to watch it too.
ฉันก็อยากดูด้วย
It's really popular, you know.
มันดังมากนะ
This song is great!
เพลงนี้เพราะจัง
Who sings it?
ใครร้องเหรอ
It's by a famous band.
เป็นเพลงของวงดัง
Do you listen to them often?
ฟังบ่อยไหม
Yeah, I stream it online sometimes.
ค่ะ บางทีก็ฟังทางอินเทอร์เน็ต
I listen to it every day.
ฉันฟังทุกวันเลย
There are so many anime characters here!
มีตัวละครอนิเมะเยอะแยะเลยนะ
Yeah, I really like that guy with the long hair.
ใช่ค่ะ ฉันชอบผู้ชายผมยาวคนนั้น
He's so cool!
หล่อจัง
Is he strong?
เขาเก่งไหม
Yeah, he's the strongest—and the kindest.
ใช่ค่ะ เก่งที่สุดและใจดีด้วย
I'm really curious about the story now.
อยากรู้เรื่องราวจัง
It airs every Friday night.
ออกอากาศทุกคืนวันศุกร์นะ
Then let's watch it together again next week!
งั้นสัปดาห์หน้ามาดูกันอีกนะ
Sounds good.
ค่ะ ไปด้วยกันค่ะ
How about watching it while snacking?
ดูไปกินขนมไปไหม
I'll bring some.
ฉันจะเอามาเอง
Scene 10: Discussion About Days Off and Part-Time Work
ฉากที่ 10: การพูดคุยเกี่ยวกับวันหยุดและงานพิเศษ
It's already 11:30 at night.
ตอนนี้ห้าทุ่มครึ่งแล้วนะ
Yeah, it's about time we went to bed.
ใช่ค่ะ ถึงเวลานอนแล้ว
What time are you waking up tomorrow?
พรุ่งนี้จะตื่นกี่โมง
I don't have work tomorrow, so I'll sleep in.
พรุ่งนี้หยุดเลย ตื่นสายหน่อย
Sure!
ดีเลยค่ะ
I have a part-time job tomorrow too.
ฉันพรุ่งนี้ก็ทำงานพิเศษ
Wait—
เอ๊ะ
You're working on Sunday too?
วันอาทิตย์ก็ทำงานพิเศษด้วยเหรอ
Yeah, starting at 9 AM.
ใช่ค่ะ เริ่มเก้าโมงเช้า
That sounds tough.
เหนื่อยนะเนี่ย
What time do you finish?
เลิกกี่โมง
I'll be done by 2 PM.
เลิกบ่ายสองโมง
So you'll have time in the afternoon, then?
งั้นตอนบ่ายก็ว่างสินะ
Yeah. I plan to do some cleaning and laundry.
ใช่ค่ะ ตอนบ่ายกะว่าจะทำความสะอาดกับซักผ้า
I'll help you clean your room.
ฉันจะช่วยทำความสะอาดห้องให้
Really?
จริงเหรอคะ
Thanks!
ขอบคุณค่ะ
You always cook for me, after all.
ค่ะ คุณทำอาหารให้ตลอดเลย
That’d be a big help.
ช่วยได้เยอะเลย ขอบคุณนะคะ
Then let's clean together starting at 3 PM tomorrow.
งั้นพรุ่งนี้บ่ายสามโมงมาทำความสะอาดกัน
Alright.
เข้าใจแล้วค่ะ
Did you check the weather forecast for tomorrow?
ดูพยากรณ์อากาศวันนี้หรือยัง
Yeah, they said it's going to be a really nice day.
ดูแล้วค่ะ พรุ่งนี้อากาศดีมากเลย
The laundry will dry quickly, then!
ผ้าซักจะแห้งเร็วแน่ๆ
Sure is.
ใช่เลยค่ะ
Alright, I'll turn off the lights.
งั้นปิดไฟแล้วนะครับ/ค่ะ
Okay. Goodnight!
ได้ค่ะ/ครับ ฝันดีค่ะ/ครับ
Goodnight!
ฝันดีนะครับ/ค่ะ
See you tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้เจอกัน